So here we want to open up some ports like for example ports for HTTP/HTP access as we have
said before and let's open also the port for MySQL and for FTP or FTP access, okay.
As shown here this is the common port that we have explained that it is needed to be
enabled. So if you can see here simply if we type sudo firewall cmd list dash all we want
to see all of the available ports or open port on this server, okay. By default the firewall
closes everything so I can't access this server by SSH. I can't copy any files by using FTP.
There is no services or no ports or protocols open. So what we'll do here is that we'll open some ports
and protocols so that I need to have specific access from these files. This is as a basic firewall
configuration. We'll not do advanced configuration like allowing some specific IP addresses. We'll
just open the basic ports. So if we here want to open the port for example for this will be
for the SSH secure port 22 it is TCP, okay. So we'll just type the same comment for all the
STMD but we'll open it as a permanent so that it's not dynamic. It will be after the server is
restarted and we use dash dash add dash port 22 TCP. As the same can be done for HTTP if I have an
alternate, if I have any conflicting service that uses port 80 I can use alternate HTTP which is
8080 okay but for me I don't have any conflicting ports so I will open these ports. Okay I mean here
for the firewall I need to open the basic ports some software or some web server I might need to
configure using the alternate port like 8080 and also here I will open the full full 3 for HTTP SSL
secure access and let's open now the 3306 if I recall this is the ports for the SQL
3306 okay and last one here is FTP port 21. So if I'm going to leave the port now should list
that we have but between not least anything before because we forgot to do some
important thing in the Linux world every step that you do you need to make a reload as
either you are managing any kind of server like web server that the server void or PBX server
you need just to reload the server so that's reload the firewall
okay you need just to type dash dash not one dash because it is case sensitive and if I can see
now we can see that the server is now the port sorry that we have here now is 2288 pull 43
3306 and 2021. Suppose now for any security reason I want just to disable the uploading for the
file okay if I am doubting about any suspicious activity for example I don't want anyone to upload
for now any files so I can remove temporary the ports 21 okay so if I want to remove the ports
I will remove it by typing the same comment cmd-perment but instead of add we'll just type remove
and we'll type the port number of 21 TCP okay and of course don't forget to reload and then
if we can see here we can see now that 22 only is the port okay and 84 443 and 3306
actually for the 22 it is very common to be enabled because it provides secure shell access
and because if you are managing any server any server in the graphical user interface it is not
very good or strong so the first server can be managed by using a common line interface especially
if you have any issue in logging or troubleshoot or taking logs for example by using graphical
user interface so it is very important to enable supports 22 okay so here let's update the system
okay let's type these comments okay and we will type these comments and after the system is updated
I will restart it and come back to you okay it will take some time so I will pause the video and come back to you
okay now so the updates are successfully installed and now we will proceed with our next task of
installation of Docker before we use Docker's or containerization in our system we need
first to remove any conflicting packages because some packages might cause problem when we install
Docker so we'll uninstall these packets these package with its dependencies so here these are the
packets of man build the and scope you let's remove them okay it will confirm the removal
and we install the yam utilities because the yam utilities it is needed to add the Docker repository
okay so let's install the yam details and confirm the installation
okay it is complete so here let's add Docker repository by by issuing this comma this is the
repository or Docker hub which contains all the Docker image that we will use in our system like
APHP Apache MySQL it is so let's install it by using the yam configuration manager
it will take some time okay it's added so without so sorry it didn't take any time
let's now install the Docker engines Docker engine actually is the client server applications
that we'll pull down the image that we can use it several times by using several tagging in
different containers so let's download it install it
okay it will just first download it and then later it will install it about 10 packages
may it might take maximum of five minutes so I will pause the video and come back to you
okay so the Docker engine now is successfully installed so we will start it it is the same
it is idea is pretty similar to the hypervisor in which we manage but we will not manage
your machine is a container inside our operating system so is the Docker is the main source
in which when we started we would continue create just the containers for different images
serving different purposes for web service SQL service etc and you can just start and stop it
as huge show so let's first we need to issue the soon to comment start the Docker
okay and let's enable it
okay the Docker now is enabled
okay if we can view its status it shows that the Docker service is active android cool
so now I'm moving to the last part of this video we will need because the Docker every time
we don't want to issue sudo to execute any Docker command so we'll add the current user
which is m number by issuing this comment it is the same idea by adding the user to the
server but we'll type sudo user modification - easy to add it to the group to add it to the group of
Docker okay so the user can use the Docker without being without every time asking
as a sudo comment because the users will be added to the Docker group so let's add the user
and for this comment to be effective here on right now we need to type new group Docker okay
and it will run but only in this terminal I mean here if this terminal is closed the user's
privilege boom is not available no more you need to to do the sudo again for the changes
to be permanent the users m number needs or I need to sign out and sign in again
so for now if I want to run any comment for example let's run Docker
hello words okay it is a ready Docker it is not fine locally so it tried to pull it from
the Docker hub okay and you can see here that hello from Docker and this message shows
that installations appears to be working correct if I want to issue any Docker command like
Docker ps-8 to see all of the doctors that I have I have only one container this is the
idea of the container this is the image of a lower okay it is run or created 16 seconds ago
and it is run with exit because it is just for testing purposes is not a real content okay
so I hope that this session is clear to you and of course if you want to ask me about
if any doubts or questions please don't hesitate to ask me thank you